howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
today's guest is nick shader nick's a
professor of behavioral science at the
university of warwick
school of business hello everybody
glad to have you here nick this should
be fun
yeah no it's a real pleasure to be
invited yeah
in fact you don't know this but i've
actually been following your work for
quite a while
particularly the work you've done with
morton christensen
on the structure and evolution of
language i went back and
looked at my records and i believe the
first paper i read by you guys
was towards a connectionist model of
recursion in human linguistic
performance which i think was around
1999. yeah that's right in fact
this very day i've been working with
morton on a
new book um that we're putting together
calls
provisioning at least a language game so
we're still working together 20 years
old
and having as much fun as ever yeah he's
a he's a fine fell i got to know him
when he was a sabbatical visitor at the
santa fe institute we were both there
and we had some some excellent
conversations so give him my regards
today we're going to talk about one of
nick's books the mind
is flat and as always you can find a
link to that book
on amazon i think on our episode page at
jimrutshow.com
now this has got a little interesting
history a little unusual for the podcast
and that i actually read the book
a while back back in late 2018 as i
checked for my records and i found it
shockingly radical
as maybe some of you will as we dig into
some of the ideas on it i
found it so radical i said to myself i
really need to read this again to come
to a firm conclusion about it
but you know the russia life many other
books to read work to be done
i didn't do it until now and i said you
know
we have quite a few people in the
cognitive science
and artificial intelligence area on the
podcast you know i really ought to reach
out to nick shader and give me an excuse
to reread the book
and maybe sharpen up my conclusions
about it a little bit
and i gotta say it it's still radical as
[ __ ]
but it holds together and what's more
it's congruent
with a great body of cognitive science
cognitive neuroscience
and lab psychology research and in
retrospect
it should have been obvious right since
2014 when i really
took seriously to trying to learn a
little bit about cognitive science and
cognitive neuroscience i think i read
75 books and maybe 300 papers and i kind
of feel like thomas huxley
and what he said about darwin's theory
of evolution
how stupid of me not to thought of that
really it's a radical idea but i can't
find any holes in it
also for those who want to learn more
about it
there's a course available at
futurelearn.com
called the mind is flat we'll have a
link to that on the website
as well at jimrutshow.com essentially
what nick is
talking about in this book is that the
view that so many of us
have had from culture from science from
literature
from clinical psychology etc that
there's great depth in the human mind
and his argument is that this is not
only
misconceived but it's just wrong right
now the very idea
that our minds contain hidden depths is
completely wrong
and he starts off with kind of an
interesting interlude
about anna karenina why don't you tell
us a little bit about
that and then let's get rolling yeah
well thank you so much jimmy it's a
wonderful intro um
yes so if you read a book uh any book
really you'll have a sense that the the
characters are
very become very real to you and one of
the things that's very interesting
is that they often seem realer than the
actual people we know
or at least as real so for example with
anna karenina you have a
character developed through the book who
you have a sense of a
tormented and troubled woman at the very
end of the book
no plot spoilers are going to be um be
objected to as she
she jumps under a train and commits
suicide and it's not quite clear to you
as the reader why she does that
but you have a still civil sense of a
rich a rich complex person and you think
well maybe
it was despair at being never being
acceptable in petersburg society because
of her
her wild lifestyle and her her affair
with her lover
perhaps the favor the lover was failing
um there are any numbers of reasons for
feeling hopeless but also it could just
have been a sort of momentary sense of
almost theatrical sort of making a
theatrical gesture without really having
thought it through at all
you're not sure and i think what's
interesting
is that you have a sense of a rich
character a deep interesting character
and one of the most the central
characters are one of the most important
books
um has ever written but you really don't
have a very clear sense of what this
character is
is doing and why and one thing you might
think is well
if this was a real life character a real
person not
not a fictional one then we could simply
ask her
you could say okay well i didn't you
seem to be a very complex
three-dimensional rich human being and
you did this extraordinary acts
then you tell me why you did it but of
course
i think when we think about that a bit
more it's sort of obvious to us that
actually anna herself in contemplating
perhaps not very very deeply
contemplating her
her last uh desperate act probably
doesn't have any particularly deep
insights we don't have ourselves
and she'll be able to tell you a story
she better think well yes i guess
what is bothering me at the moment i
think it must be this it's the
it's the hopeless the hopeless romantic
relationship like what was happening
tangled in right
it's the fact that i didn't probably see
my child or it's the fact that i
i'm going to be ostracized by the
aristocracy of
petersburg and moscow but actually she's
speculating just as much as we are
and i think that even if you would
suppose imagine that she were to
uh survive the the incident and and you
could ask her in her
recuperating as i imagine it in the book
in swiss sanatorium
because i look back and think through
why why are you engaged in that act and
again
my feeling is that i'm trying to put
sort of push on your intuition that
that process of looking back at
something one did i'm trying to work out
why did i do that
that's really pretty similar in fact
very very similar i think to the process
of trying to understand why a fictional
character or another person did
something
what you're doing is you're looking at
your behavior looking at your uh
experiences and trying to piece together
what must have been going on
but what you can't do is as it were
look inside some kind of deep um
inner self and think well hang on other
people have to speculate about my
motives but i can just see them
they're just written in my instrument by
some sort of
vault inside my mind you know let me
have a quick look and ruffle through
and i'll tell you what the what it says
but i think that's
that's that's we all know that to be
illusory and in fact it was if you ask
people
to explain their behavior several times
they often give you
different or at least not perfectly
aligned answers because we don't fully
understand ourselves so really i want
what i wear when i want to go
as an intuition pump at the beginning of
the book and obviously here too is to
make one think well this is an odd thing
because we have a sense of a rich
character of anaconda we have a
sense of rich characters in people
around us and in ourselves
and i don't want to understand at all
the complexity of humanity human beings
we are standing
i think in some ways that the idea that
our mind has mental depths actually
obscures we'll talk about this later i'm
sure obscures how
unbelievably creative and clever we are
and what extraordinary beings we are
and so i'm not wanting to in any way
reduce
the remarkable nature of human cognition
um but i do think we should
sort of allow the possibility that when
i'm trying to understand my own actions
or anna's trying to understand her
actions or i'm trying to understand
the actions of another person or a
fictional character i'm really doing the
same thing
and the final point is that when you
think about fictional characters
i think this is a this is a bit of a
shocker when you think about fictional
characters it's obvious that there's no
right answer so if i ask you well come
on then what is what is the reason that
anna jumped under the tray
really and truly and of course there's
no real answer to that because
it's just a story there is no there's no
deep um
question of which can be settled by
investigating anna's brain because there
is no anna with no brain
however however i think that's exactly
the right approach
we should be having when we're thinking
about other people and ourselves too
it's not the case that actually if you
could scan anna's brain a critical
moment you could read off
the fact that her real motivation was
one thing or another
i think that's that's a that's itself an
illusion
so i think the the creation of stories
about ourselves is something we do all
the time
we can create more and less convincing
stories and we can argue about the
stories
but the idea that there's some kind of
ground truth is
is a dangerous mistake i think so it
doesn't mean that you cannot have
sensible debates about why you acted as
you did just as you can for literary
characters so if i said
anna's concern was i don't know
primarily um a despair at a state of the
service
you could reasonably say well that's you
know signing that in the rest of the
book doesn't seem to be it's almost
about them lots of other people are and
in which case you'd have a
you'd have a beverly good argument so
it's not that you can say anything
but the idea that there's a kind of
ground truth that you can get at
is no more true i think for fictional
characters than is of ourselves there's
no
there's no real sense which says that
the real answer deeping lurking deep
within me
yeah i found that very good as you say
intuition pump to
kind of compare and contrast you know
maybe we're not that different than a
fictional character
and of course the other side of the
argument kind of what you're
arguing against i suppose is what
started to manifest in the late 19th
century
and then through the kind of the late
mid-20th century
depth psychology freud young and those
characters
in fact i'm going to read more than
usual number of brief quotes from the
book
to kind of get a sense of your position
where you're coming from
no amount of therapy dream analysis word
association experiment or brain scanning
can recover a person's true motives not
because they are difficult to find but
because there is nothing to find
it is not hard to plumb our metal depths
because they are so deep and so murky
because there are no mental depths to
plum right quite the opposite of the
depth psychology guys
no one at any point in human history has
ever been guided by inner beliefs or
desires
any more than any human being has been
possessed by evil spirits or watched
over by a guardian angel
and another the very idea of looking
into our own minds embodies the mistake
we talk as if we have a faculty of
introspection to scrutinize the contents
of our inner world just as we have
faculties of perception
to inform us about the external world
but introspection is a process
not a perception but of invention the
real-time generation interpretation and
explanations to make sense of our own
world and actions
the inner world is a mirage and then
finally but of all this depth richness
and endless scope for exploration
it's utterly fake so you don't hold back
here
at first i thought this was repetitious
but i i did find it actually helpful to
kind of move me psychologically off the
ball
of you know what we've kind of
culturally found through our you know
religions and depth psychology etc
that there's all this stuff there to be
discovered
yes i think that's it it is a very hard
shift to make
um and i think it's something that on
the one hand seems as you're hinting in
your introduction
one hand seems incredibly plausible and
intuitive and another
on the other hand seems just completely
crazy and i think one
tends to oscillate between the two
perspectives and i think it takes quite
a long time to think to feel comfortable
with the fact that this
this sense that we have of being being
driven by
what you've mysteriously hidden from us
is actually just the wrong way to see
things um so i think
i mean again i mean thinking about
fictional characters i think is a good
way in because because there in some
sense you want to be able to say well of
course
um characters in books they're kind of
in some loose
sort of metaphorical sense driven by
emotions emotions and some so on because
when i tell a story about why they did
what they did i'll say well
her motive there was this i think i
think she probably thought this was true
or she thought that
fronski wasn't in fact being faithful to
her or maybe she didn't um but i'm i'm
giving you a rationalization a story
but of course i don't really think i
don't really think it's that's that
story is somehow
instantiated known as anna's brain and
she's driven her behavior
and i think that's the the critical
trick is to realize that that's not
really true for
for understanding other people and
ourselves either um
so that so one one reason to to think
this is that
when we look at the stories we tell
about ourselves of all shapes and sizes
whether they're complex stories or
everyday stories
about why we do things the sound and
consistent truth is that the stories we
tell don't seem to fit together
so you ask you asked me why i did
something and i'll give you
i'll tell you and you asked me well tell
me more about that why did you do that
that particular way i'll
amazingly i'll just keep on talking it's
you know we're amazing spinners of yarns
so i can keep on going as if there's
this enormous
library full of self-understanding i can
draw on
so like why did you you take that
particular route and say oh well it's
pretty busy on
the other routes and and there's also
just a little more scenic
and why is it more scenic what would you
say about what makes it more scenic and
i can tell you a story about that and i
can just go on
indefinitely so you can either conclude
from this well first of all the
the richness of my explanation is
suspicious because every time you probe
it
more appears and you might think well
have i just got this whole
whole book loads of information just
waiting there to uh
um to answer your every question all
ready to go or am i in fact
making it up as i go along and i'm just
thinking gosh you've got me there i
i'll cook up an answer oh here's an
answer go give me a new question oh
i'll give you a new answer to that and
of course if i'm improvising if i'm
doing that creative
making it up as i go along thing you
should be able to catch me out because
you should find that the answers i'm
giving aren't referring back to some
common source some sort of um
fixed book of my mind which is which is
just guides that my
my every action of thought instead
i'm like a novelist spinning a story and
my my
characters and the different learns of
the plot or it's inevitably if i'm not
very very careful
going to get tangled up and not quite
make sense there's going to be various
inconsistencies creeping me
and and the truth is when you ask people
about that that's exactly what you see
inconsistencies everywhere
yeah i think i got halfway there
interestingly and as i was sort of
processing
this morning my reaction to reading the
book was you know
while i should have gotten all the way
there i was sort of halfway there
in that i had looked quite carefully at
mike gazaniga's split brain
research and you know his strong
evidence
are just very fluid confabulation right
we just make [ __ ] up right to make the
story as consistent as possible
and you do go through a lot of that kind
of evidence so let's
start talking a little bit about the
evidence that supports the argument and
let's start with where you do with
visual processing and the grand illusion
yes yes so i think this is a very
interesting place to start because and
this is
something that's been much talked about
in philosophy and psychology and
starting
not with alvaro and daniel dennison and
many other
important philosophers and psychologists
and so this is the idea this question
but when we consider the world around us
sort of look about
we have a sense of enormous richness
this is an illusion that very similar to
the illusion we're going to come to in a
minute it's an illusion now we're
thinking just about perception not
thinking about
our beliefs and beliefs but we'll see
that this is very parallel
so we think as i look around the world i
think yes it's fully colorful everywhere
and seen in crisp and clear detail
if i look at a picture of some text or a
page of text i think i see words
everywhere
maybe how many words do i see at once i
don't know 50. um probably a
whole page worth but you know a lot i
see that i see
a lot of words everywhere i look at a
school photograph
i think well i'm seeing it's i'm
recognizing all these people
maybe not all the ones in the far
distant periphery but i'm having a sense
that
they're also recognizable so i have this
really rich sense of my
visual environment and yet and yet we
know that
that we know that is an illusion for
very basic physiological reasons
apart from lots of clever experiments so
the basic very basic physiological
reasons which we all know very well from
school biology but tend to conveniently
forget well first of all let's take
color there are two types of cell in the
eye that detect color
uh there were cone cells and and rod
cells so cone cells detect color
sorry detect color and rod cells just
really detect
uh particular motion if they're black
and white detectors
so they don't see color now the cone
cells are very concentrated in the
around the favir that's the center of
the visual field so as i look at
something that
part of my retina that is the light will
be falling on is the a little
clump of cells really dense about one
between one and two degrees initial
angle it tapers off outside that
and that is where the cone cells live
now there's a little
around 10 degrees out except till about
10 degrees out there are some
cells but not very many so it's roughly
true
that your all of your color vision is in
a little channel it's a bit like a
little
headlight so when you're looking right
at a patch of color you can
you can read off its color if you go
very far outside the patch
you haven't got the cells to do it you
simply can't possibly know what color
anything is
and that's really weird because when i
look at the world now i think well
that's just wrong isn't it i see color
everywhere
but actually that's not the case so
let's just hold that thought for one
but it's not just color it's also detail
so the
for the cells the the the cone cells in
the fever are also what
process um detail detailed sort of
structure and for that matter if you go
too far outside the
periphery of vision the image is simply
blurry in fact
very blur if you went to 20 or 30
degrees uh out outside of the visual
uh center so if you look if i look at
something and think
how how much can i see 20 or 30 degrees
off the center from where i'm looking
um well the answer is it can't be very
much because the image is horrendously
blurry but
again i have no perception of that so i
have a sense that the world is in
perfectly clear focus i see all the
detail it's like see all the color
but we know that's wrong now where does
that illusion come from
what's driving it and i think the answer
to that
um there's of two perspectives actually
i should say this
it's not um not just one one view in
this area
then one perspective would say ah
filling in what your brain is doing is
it's getting really detailed and
radical information from the from the
favir
but it's it's sort of guessing about the
rest of things
so that's one possibility we're
basically guessing and when we as we
move our eye around we want to adjust
the guesses and
see where they're right where they're
wrong that's one possibility but the
other possibility is that
we're in fact not filling in um in fact
what we're doing instead
is just sampling a tiny portion of the
image
and the sense that we see everything
comes from the fact
that as soon as i wonder about any
aspect of the visual image
if i think what color is that or what
words that or who's that
in the in the picture i can immediately
answer the question
so the idea is that i haven't got the
answer pre-loaded and i haven't guessed
it either
it's just that as soon as you ask me if
i ask myself a question
about color or shape or the identity of
a word or anything
is else incredibly speedily my eye could
flick
into action look at the thing read off
the color or shape or
the identity of the word and before you
know it in fact within a couple of 300
milliseconds
there's an answer and that's so quick
but essentially it's instantaneous to me
it's as if i've got this information
loaded into my mind so i
think of myself and in some sense i
really am as having the world as it were
at my visual
visual fingertips ask me anything about
the world around me i can answer it
and that's what it that's what it is
according to the second view
to feel that the world is as it were
present to you
in complete detail it's not that you've
actually loaded this
into your brain at all is that you have
it ready
to sample and extract so speedily that
since you can improvise the answer so
quickly that you have the feeling that
the answer was
already there and i think that's an
interesting
uh first of all it's very interesting in
itself that our
intuitions about our perception are so
wrong so we have the feeling of this
great richness of the
sexual world and that's absolutely not
the case in fact
we're giving it an illustration of that
in a moment but it's also
an interesting clue about our creative
abilities as
uh and improvisational abilities as
cognizers where we're phenomenal
improvisers and when we're
because we're such good improvisers we
don't realize we're improvising
so we you asked me a question about the
color of some distant objects and i'll
tell you
and i think well i saw that all along i
knew that that color was i just you've
asked me and i've told you but
i had that loaded in my head but in fact
if i wasn't looking at it i really
didn't have it
in my head but i could answer the
question so fast it feels as if i did i
think that's true when we're
answering questions about our
motivations and our beliefs and so on
you give me a question i can answer it
and it's so speedy am i with my answer
that i think i didn't just make that up
that was in there now i knew the answer
to that
i'm going to give a couple of quick
examples in the perceptual context
one i think is really astounding
intuitively
but has been known for a long time in
ibm research so this goes back to
work in keith rayner's lab now dead
sadly a very
remarkable pioneer of eye movement
research
so in his early work when he was at mit
he went to amherst after that i think
ucsd
towards the end of his career very early
days at mit in the 70s
he started working on a very simple but
very interesting
paradigm so you read a sentence which is
presented to you on a screen on a
computer
and as you do do it they track your eyes
so they have
a simple setup for watching where your
eyes go so you can see that the eyes
quite accurately move
as you hop across the screen so when
you're reading a sentence
you will be essentially jumping word by
word by word roughly
sometimes short words get jumped over
and long words you read in a couple of
jumps
but essentially your eyes hopping bounce
bounce bounce burns bounce across the
screen
in discrete lumps it might actually
another illusion we have
is that it feels as if our eyes are
moving smoothly when we read
from left to right but in fact that's
not right i'm using
jumps um oh and here's another thing
actually if we just
think about the illusory nature of
perception another thing that's also
interestingly true is when you move your
eye you're essentially blind
you can't see anything while the eye is
in motion and so you also
so as you look as you read you have a
strange interplay of
picking up information complete
blindness picking up information
complete blindness
uh again we're completely oblivious to
that too
anyway the important thing is what rayna
was able to do
um with the information about where i
was looking and that was to feed that
back to the computer
and to change what's on the screen in
consequence
so the clever trick was thinking well
what would it be like
if we give you a a line of text
and only where you were looking fairly
exactly in fact
the critical window turned out to be
about 15 characters long
15 characters around where you're
looking in fact five going to the left
10 to the right if we read left to right
it's like we're slightly more interested
in what's coming next than what we just
read
you're going to have a 15 character
window which is unchanged untouched
no funny funny business but all the
other all the rest of the words in the
line of text will be x's or latin or
anything you like
so what you're going to do is you're
going to read a text
where as you as your eyes go from left
to right as they bounce across the
screen
the actual text itself will change so
wherever you're looking text will appear
as if you're seeing the the whole
sentence but when you're not looking
then you've just got x's so so if i were
looking over your shoulder as you were
doing this experiment
i'd see a line of x's with some coherent
text and coherent text was
start on the left it would go bounce
bounce bounce bounce bounce across the
screen
so to me it would seem like a really
weird thing uh i
see this strange pattern of orderly
meaningful words
moving across a sea of exes or latin or
something else
but if i asked you in the experiment
well
you know how does that feel the answer
would be well how did what feel i was
just reading some text
if i said well did you notice anything
funny about do you see any x's did you
see any latin
the answer is no i was just reading text
normally there's nothing funny going on
i just read like i normally read and the
point is that the
the most shocking is that if you give
someone
this kind of what's called gauge
contingent display so that you're
you're driving what they see based on
the location of their eyes
you can give them a little tiny window
of information around where they're
looking
and the rest can be essentially junk and
they will never know the difference
now it feels like the full text is
available to them they can see the whole
sentence
and andrew's water in some sense that's
right because as soon as they want to go
back
let me just check back i missed the
beginning of the sentence i'll check
back quickly
it appears just as you go to look at it
it appears um
you want to go jump and jump forwards a
bit that will appear too
so you have the sense that there's this
full sentence is there for you
it's at your fingertips and it's what it
is but it really isn't present
um because in fact the the stimulus has
been
large chunks that have been deleted and
the same principle applies not just
text that applies to anything so if i
showed you a school photo
and you look at a particular face but
all the other faces are slightly blurred
that's you're never going to notice that
either as long as where whichever face
you're looking at i make sure to unblur
that one just as you look at it
then you'll think they're all in perfect
focus and in fact that has to be right
because
actually where you're not looking the
world is blurred that's
that's just the way it is it's blurred
it's pretty colorless and it's not very
detailed
um but we don't notice because we're not
looking um so i think
that's that's both weird and interesting
in itself and i think also gives you a
sense that it would be slightly odd to
think of the filling in stories being
right because if i if i'm just reading a
page of text it seems a bit weird to say
i'm filling in all the text that's
coming and all the texts happened i mean
yeah i'm ready yeah how could i be
filling in the next stuff it seems a bit
of a strange perspective
but i think a better better perspective
is to say you know your sense of the
thing
being real to you is the sense that
asking ask yourself a question about it
and you can answer it really fast
and to that i think the same sense we
have when we think about our own
our own uh motivations and beliefs and
so on
yeah it's really interesting and and you
actually
answered a question that i had while i
was reading i said why would evolution
have created this sense of more
completeness than
is really there and the answer you gave
is the real world is
relentlessly consistent for facts to
hold good in the same world they cannot
be contradictory and then you also said
however
inconsistency and sparseness are not
just characteristics of fiction they are
also the hallmarks
of mental life so interestingly you know
i took away from your words
that evolution has been playing a very
clever
grand illusion which is to approximate
the consistency of the real world with
very sparse and inconsistent data a
pretty cool trick
yeah i think that's exactly right yeah
that's exactly what what the brain is
doing
and if we had mostly opposite subjective
experience if you imagine
that every time you looked at something
it suddenly sprang into detail and color
and when you looked away it faded into
murky colorlessness you
have the sense that the world was
changing but the world isn't changing
you've just changed where you're looking
um and when you look back there it is
again looking um looking
bright and colorful so we have the the
sense that
what perception is trying to tell me is
what the world's actually like and if
the world is not changing i'm just
moving my eyes
and i don't want the brain to be saying
goodness me everything's getting very
there's color appearance oh it's gone
again it's come back detail's appearing
it's going it's coming
that there's no actual change in the
world so i don't want to confuse the
system by
by seeing changes where there aren't any
and the other point about consistency i
think is crucial because
the real world has to be consistent
inevitably so that means that when i
just of course if you're in a devious
psychological experiment that gets
strained a little bit because then you
can start to mess with people so you can
get them to look
look around the picture and at one
moment they're looking at one thing then
they look at it again and you can change
what they saw
and see if they noticed so you could
start to start to mess with that but but
normally the
world doesn't play horrible tricks on us
too often and so
and we you know we get along fine with
this this uh perspective
but i think what we when we go wrong is
thinking
when we imagine ourselves introspecting
we're thinking that's the same thing
the thing is with interest with with
perception
there's a physical solid external world
which is
um generating the data that we're
analyzing when we're
introspecting we're not looking into
some inner world the value is no inner
world
what we're doing is we're interpreting
um our behavior
and our thoughts we're trying to make
sense of our actions
but we're not able to do that by viewing
as it were viewing some of the contents
of some sort of inner reality
and the trouble is because we're trying
to make sense of ourselves because
that's a
fundamentally creative process just as
if we're trying to
make sense of a fictional character or
another person that is not a pro there's
not a solid thing we're perceiving here
we're not perceiving anything um we're
inventing
and the inventions will turn out to be
very very sparse
and also very inconsistent yeah you gave
a wonderful example where you move from
the issues with our external perception
to our internal perception
you know take a mental image and see
what you actually know of it you tell
an interesting story about the tiger
maybe you could tell that story
yes so i think most of us have the
intuition that we can
imagine a tiger pretty pretty clearly
and certainly
um we see ties and other things in
dreams and have a sense of it
it was very it was almost it was like it
was really there so
my question to myself was to think well
uh and this is actually
this original example probably goes
further than this but it goes back
certainly to
zenon pollution um psychologists and
computer scientists
interested in in imagery so the question
is to ask yourself some questions about
your image of a timeline so the thing
that pollution
used to focus on is to say oh how many
stripes are there on its tail uh to
which the answer is oh yeah
well i ought to know the answer to that
because i mean in fact imagine it like
clearly
but let's not leave aside the stripes of
his tail uh because that's that's
uh used to be really the um the question
is to think how the stripes work around
the body at all
so for example you might think well what
direction are the stripes right as they
go
go along the body if they go along a
long ways or around the tiger
the tiger's body then what about the
legs i mean how do they go
um so you try to try to imagine maybe a
tiger's
stripes go maybe round the legs and
maybe maybe around the body so
but what happens when they join together
and how does that how does the stripy
pattern
join between the legs and the body how
does that work and
um it just gets very baffling now
if you were to look at a picture of a
tiger which i recommend that people
might do
um you'll find that actually quite
largely part of the tiger there are the
crucial tricky bits to some degree
don't have stripes at all they're just
not striped so
that actually some of the questions
you're asking yourself there's an answer
which is
oh that's a white bit well there's just
no stripes there and until you look at
the tiger you just
you can't imagine that at all you've
also got a question of how the strikes
work around the face and it's just
yeah it's just something that when you
see a side you think of course that's
the only way it could be
try to envisage one try and count the
strikes try to imagine how they go how
they interface with each other
it's absolutely hopeless and i think
this is a really
general sort of trick that our mind is
playing once you get we have to sense
that
we can reconstruct you know
animals um people's faces uh all sorts
of
letters actually if you just try to and
some of you when they have to do this
but
try to write a typical level lowercase g
as printed in something like times new
roma what does that look like
and i'm just trying to imagine it now i
know it's pretty weird
but it's not it's not like a g of
handwriting that's for sure and yet this
is something i've seen you we've all
seen
literally hundreds of thousands that's
millions of times in our life
we can't even remember very clearly what
that looks like
yeah i couldn't tell you it's
interesting yeah let's dig in a little
bit we are a little
short of time because there's so much
interesting here let's make sure we move
along
one of the things that's you know sort
of key on your
argument is that basically everything is
perceptual
processing and that includes memory
which it first seems you know a little
contradictory a little off-putting
but again there are arguments from
cognitive science that
memories are really nothing much more
than snapshots of perception
could you talk a little bit about and
this is an area i'm very interested in a
lot of my work goes in here in the area
the linkage between consciousness memory
perception and attention
so maybe give your thoughts on what
memory traces are
actually and how our processing of
memory is very similar or perhaps
identical to our processing of
perception
yeah yeah absolutely so i think the
intuition is that we often have is that
perception is kind of front end to the
mind it sort of
filters the filters the input makes
sense of it and then we
store some kind of abstract
representation of the output we pop this
into a memory
uh and that memory system might be
really different from the way perception
works it's just a
next stage in the process as it were and
i think that's a very misleading way to
think
in fact i think it's misleading really
to think of memory even really
existing as a separate thing we clearly
remember lots of stuff
but the idea that there's a which is
somehow separate from the
the process of uh picking up and
perceiving the information i think is
is a misguided one so this is a
sometimes known as a proceduralist view
of memory
so according to this sort of idea you've
got to what you've got is a
a set of mechanisms for for perceiving
the world
or indeed for that match we're also
acting on it so if you're thinking about
remembering
how to swing a golf club um some said
too that's
that's you swung a golf club lots of
times maybe in which case
um you know that your memory for doing
that swinging is not stop it's not
really stored
somewhere separately from the motor
commands that actually allow you to do
this
to swing the club on a particular
occasion it's just simply an
accumulation of all those
all those actions and similarly if
you're thinking about your
memory of of particular people or events
or
tigers those are things you have
perceived in real time as you've
encountered them
and those perceptions leave a trace
it's not that they produce an output a
kind of they sort of
it would give their verdict and say ah
what happened there was this
i pop that in the memory bank it's more
that they
um that that the process of
understanding the world from all away
from the details of the
low-level vision visual features all the
way up to
what was happening there was that person
angry or happy or
wherever they're going with that
implement whatever it was
all of that is that process is simply
laying a trace as it were
in situ so the idea from this
perspective and that is rather a radical
perspective
idea is that if you have damage to a
part of the brain that is involved in
some aspects of perception you should
also have trouble
with imagining or imaging that aspect of
the world
and also you should have trouble
remembering it too unless you recoded
that memory in a different form
so the thought here would be um if if
for example you have area to
damage to an area in visual cortex which
is concerned with say color or motion
whatever it may be let's say color
then you will struggle to see colors
and process them but you'll also find
you can't imagine them either
and also when you remember images of
objects you won't know what color they
are now you might have remembered in
words
pillar boxes are red in the uk um i know
that i've there's
a verb observable information i've got
so in that case i can answer the
question what color is the pillar box
but if i try and visualize a pillar box
if i've had damage to my visual cortex i
can't do it because the memories are
stored in the same place as the
perception or in case of
actions the the the memory of house play
tennis is stored in the same set
circuits that are actually
controlling tennis playing and i think
in general
we tend to miss this because we don't
think of perception
as as abstract as it really is so you
might say to yourself well yeah but i
mean perceiving is one thing that's just
sort of knowing what
objects are there are what color they
are but when i'm
watching a movie or talking to a friend
i'm thinking about
so much more than that i'm thinking
about your intentions and purposes
um speculating about human nature
or i might be thinking about a
mathematical problem and trying to
do a different geometry of my mind or
might be trying to work out how to put
together
a piece of furniture and all of these
things i think you should view those as
continuous with perception
and they're all tasks which are
basically taking data from the sensors
and trying to work out what to do with
it
and once we think of this as a
relatively abstract
uh not not just not just rooted in kind
of
the colors and shapes in front of us but
as a process of abstract pattern
construction and that's really that's
really a good chunk of cognition just
all about that now having said that of
course what
makes us very good at this kind of task
is that we're not
just locked into the current sensory
input
so i can i can shut my eyes as it were
and think about lots of things which
where there's no sensory input coming in
to me because i have all those past
impressions
past thoughts which i can which i can
review but they themselves are just in
the same format they're the same kind of
thing
they're just sort of past perceptual
traces past
memories memories of past perceptual
experiences rather than
being in a completely different form
interesting now one thing that you
didn't talk about much
and when i do focus a lot on my own work
is as you'd say
that you did say that perception is not
just a simple
screenshot of what our eyes see because
as you go through carefully
our eyes don't see a screenshot they see
a whole bunch of little things
but one of the high-level processings
which seems ubiquitous
pretty much quite a ways down in the
phylogenic stack as far as something
like consciousness goes
is the ability to find objects we
perceive
our existence in the sensorium as full
of objects not
chunks of color and shape and lines and
edges
we have it seemingly at least seems to
me and a lot of the research i've seen
a very deep hardwired machine for
finding
objects and in fact there appears to be
an
object store in the parietal regions of
the brain you know the famous
mariah carey neuron etc that you
stimulate a specific neuron
and you pull up a very specific object
or a
general object like dogs or tables etc
how does the concept of objects fit in
to your sense of perception and memory
yeah well i think that it's a very i
think it's very central
concept actually um so i want to
so there's one thing i've asked you
quite a lot in the book is that
that we're only we're incredibly serial
processors
so we can only really do one thing at a
time and
in perceptual terms i think roughly a
way to put that is to say we can
perceive essentially one essentially one
object
so i think of an old objects as in a way
themselves psychologically very very
fundamental because they're the sort of
the unit
that the perceptual system can grab hold
of now that means for example that if
i'm looking at a word
uh i can't see other words going back to
the eye tracker
as i read a sentence roughly speaking my
eyes jump
word by word by word as i mentioned
before you sometimes jump some more
words which are
predictable you can just guess those um
and for long complicated words you
sometimes
need to look at them more than once
essentially you
read the beginning and then the end but
the yeah broadly speaking
you're picking up one word at a time and
although you have this feeling that you
receive all the other words that they're
not they're not really there
now i think the so that's one one
interesting
interesting thing that the the units
there may be sort of basic level of unit
that we can
grab hold off perceptually but another
interesting thing you
might one might think is what but aren't
words made of letters
so if i can perceive say a word dog well
i'm sure i'm perceiving not
it must be perceiving three things d o
and g because dog is
um is made of three letters so i must
must be able to see three things as well
as once kind of weird
three in one trinity in case of the dog
but actually i think that's misleading
too
because i think if you ask people to
focus on the letter
they can't see the word if you ask them
to focus on the word they can't see the
letter at least there's huge
interference between
them so there again it appears when
intuitively first one can see lots of
words and to see all the letters within
them
but actually i think that's not right um
so
let me give you an example from speech
perception which i think i've talked
talk about
which is the phoneme restoration effect
so this is a
lovely effect where you play a word and
you splice out a bit of it and replace
it with white noise
so it sounds like a word with a cough
and the question that the subject is
asked is
uh where was the white noise what did
you miss so the famous example is
you you pray some of the word
legislature and i think it's the sir
um you take out the sir and you just
replace it with a with a cough
as it were it's just essentially just
pure white ones and the question is well
where
where was the where was the cough and
people are hopeless of this
they they often the great the the cough
to the boundaries of the words it was
just before just after
and just generally they have generally
have no idea what they missed
and so that's really very nice because
that's telling you that you perceive the
word
you know you heard the word in this case
the rather strange and unusual word
legislature you're pretty sure of that
but you don't actually know which sound
you heard um if i asked you did you hear
the s do you think well i don't know i
think i probably did but you're wrong
you didn't hear the yes that was the bit
that was chopped out
but you just simply don't know and that
you know that sort of phenomenon
you think is everywhere in perception um
if you perceive a hole you don't really
perceive that the parts
and if you see one hole you don't
perceive other holes
yeah a lot of that another example which
is that
sorry go ahead i was going to mention
that you know the the field of gestalt
psychology has
been drilling into this for a long time
right we perceive a car
as a whole but if we focus and there's
some even some interesting thought about
at what angle do you focus etc
a car has tires and handles and a roof
and a
boot as you'd say in the uk etc but when
we're just seeing things go by on the
road we just perceive them holistically
as cars it takes an additional level of
effort and attention and we'll talk
about attention in a minute
to decompose an object into its
components but you probably
as you point out you can do one or the
other you can perceive the car as a
whole or you can perceive the tires but
you probably can't do both
right simultaneously and again this has
to do with this granular but probably
hierarchical structure of objects that
we're operating in
let me drill into another question that
i had which is
you don't other than very much in
passing dig into the distinction if
there is one and maybe
your work would say there isn't one
between the different kinds of
memory with respect to their contents
and then i'm thinking particularly
episodic memory i.e rethinking the
dinner i had with my daughter last night
versus
declarative memory paris is the capital
of france
do you think there is any difference or
are they just projections we put on to
what are essentially a unitary memory
process
yeah i mean i think i'm not a i mean
this isn't a central thing in my
thinking a certain point in my thinking
though i think it's very very important
issue
so yeah my natural my natural starting
point given
the general perspective i've been
outlining is to think of everything as
fundamentally episodic
so all you really have is a
rich collection of specific experiences
which
and you're pretty pre you run through
your life processing these experiences
as they come into you
and they leave a trace and then we'll
come and then those traces will
affect how you process the new traces
but the
so essentially everything's everything's
episodes but we normally think of
episodic memory and psychology of course
when
i can as it were pick out when the
episode was
so if i say how do you know i know that
a particular restaurant
has changed its decor you might think
well i know that because i was only
there last friday
not not so true at the moment of course
in a pandemic but you'd think in the
normal course of events i was only there
last friday
i remember the event i remember going in
and thinking yeah wow they've changed
that acro so you have in that case a
clear
sense of where the uh where the episodic
route is
and i think a semantic memory that or
declarative memory
this broader knowledge of things like um
the earth goes around the sun rather
than the sun goes around the earth and
parasitic capital france and so on
i think of those those things as it's
fundamentally the same kind of
episodic memory we've just lost lost the
episode
so if you ask me um who told who first
told you
that paris was the capital of france and
the answer is oh i've just no idea
it's just it's just people are always
saying it as it were
and when was it that you realized that
the earth went around the sun
sometime long ago i don't know the
difference from my mind would be
not the what you can do with the
information is just whether it's
traceable or not
now i know there are some arguments
looking at for example the effects of
brain damage which appear to show
that you can get damage to one memory
not the other in fact the one you
normally get is damage to the episodic
system so if you believe that there's
episodes and there's this more general
knowledge
um then it that seems to be uh
seems to be strengthened by the
observation that if you have certain
kinds of
brain damage and also for people with
very severe alcoholism
um you can get a loss of semantic sorry
episodic memory so you can
have real difficulty remembering much
about your life and where you were
yesterday and
almost your life story starts to
collapse
but you may still know a fair amount
about perhaps being in
france that's going around the sun and
so on um but i think actually
uh at least this is not a unique view to
me at all there's a very standard
counter to that is to say yeah but
actually what those people have is a
general
loss of episodes and that
shows up much worse when you ask them
about specific episodes because
specific specific episodes have been
damaged but if you ask them general
things
then any other number of episodes will
help them answer the question so if you
if you ask me about whether the paris
capital of france since there's lots and
lots of memories which will turn at the
answer to that
then i only have to find one of them but
it's really a hard question to say
what was the last movie you saw because
i have to pick out a particular episode
so it's just a tough task for difficulty
problem and you see this all over the
place in
psychology that when you have a single
set of tasks but some are harder than
others and then you damage
people have damage or difficulty then
they can't do the hard things and it can
do the easy ones it's easy to think ah
right well probably just hard and easy
tasks are done by different systems
maybe different brain areas
that's the mistake i think what we may
be falling into there but it's a it's a
complex and naughty area this so i
although i am really fond and i was fond
of
and wanting to push the episodic
perspective
um yeah i think that's that's not
something i can honestly say that this
is a resolved question in psychology
interesting i actually had an idea when
i was reading your book in that range
which was
you talk quite a bit which we'll get to
later that much of brain
processing is whole brain or nearly
whole brain processing
of one snapshot at a time and then it
produces an output that's written to
memory and i said hmm i wonder if there
are
kind of stripped down mini episodes
essentially where all the unnecessary
details are eliminated and so for
instance there's an entity that kind of
looks like an episodic memory but it's
less
rich but just says paris is the capital
of france
and every time i think that thought it
gets rewritten so
we kind of combine these two thoughts to
the one you just said is that
you know paris is the capital of france
may exist in this stripped-down
semi-episodic memory hundreds or
thousands of times
right so sure it would be preserved over
damage
more than others now the other form of
memory that
you didn't address much although again a
little bit in passing and here
the evidence from damage is stronger
that it's different
is procedural memories right we learn
how to play the piano
or ride a bike and even if we have
complete elimination of both hemispheres
of the hippocampus that seems to be
preserved that seems like maybe that is
a different animal
yeah well again i i want to say i don't
think it is
necessarily different but the the thing
that is different
is that certain kinds of procedural
memories are going to be engaging
particular
cognitive processes so different brain
regions
so if it's the case for example that
playing the piano is
broadly speaking subserved by a
relatively small subset
and it won't be that small but a
relatively small subset of brain areas
or such that you can lose a fairly large
chunk of cortex which i think you can
and some people would have and still be
able to play the piano successfully
then because you've got essentially
dedicated neural hardware for this
problem
that that hardware can keep running now
most problems we
engage in don't really have or most of
most
things we do in daily life don't really
have a dedicated hardware
but if you do some repetitive tasks
for hundreds of thousands of hours you
may well develop some
dedicated hardware to do that task and
reading would be another thing
to some extent language too the language
does use a wolf a lot of lots of brain
because of all the high level
inferential stuff to actually figure out
what what's worth saying
but um if you have a special dedicated
brain region for something
then then that rather breaks this idea
that you can only do one thing at a time
the the reason that the brain is such a
serial
process and what the reason it does one
thing at a time is that
it works as a giant distributed network
so the calculations it's doing the
processing it's doing
are spread across billions of billions
of neurons
which are all working interdependently
in a cooperative fashion
so that means that if you're trying to
solve one problem with a big cooperative
network of neurons then you can't get
the same
network of neurons to do another problem
at the same time because they're going
to get muddled up
so that implies that if you're doing a
task where you don't have a special
dedicated piece of machinery or set up
you have to cook something together on
the fly with the
range of mental mechanisms you have
lying around
that's going to take up a lot of brain
and that's going to basically wipe out
the ability to do
anything else very complicated but if
you have a dedicated
brain with neural machinery then then
you may be able to do
run that thing and still do something
else so for example touch typists
um are able to read
text and type it if they practice this a
great deal
while still for example holding a
conversation in fact they won't have any
memory of what they've
been typing but they can just look at it
look at the text type it type it out
and they can think about other things
they can have a chat they can do that
because they've
basically built this very very
specialized piece of machinery over
hundreds and hundreds of hours of
practice
i actually saw that i actually saw i had
a an executive assistant
back in the i guess it was early 80s and
she was an old school
secretary before she became an executive
assistant she could type 70 words a
minute
and carry on a conversation with me you
know what the hell
right very impressive it's amazing
it's an absolutely amazing thing to see
yes the fact that um
it's just become a sort of completely
automated automated process
and it takes hundreds of hours to do it
of course similarly with piano playing
so when we're learning to play the piano
we're learning to type it
initially we don't have any special we
haven't constructed any machinery to do
it yet
so it's using our whole brain is
struggling away
trying to keep the process on track so
any slight interruption will completely
scramble your typing or your piano play
but once you once you're a master then
you can type furiously you can
play a piano piece not with great beauty
and expression necessarily but you'll be
able to play it
while having a conversation because that
all of that that lower level stuff has
been
some degree automated having said that
this automation isn't perfect so
we tend to for example to imagine for
example that when we're driving
we can um we can uh drive on obviously
pilots and we think yeah i can i can see
that i can do that because look i can
have a conversation i can see the radio
i can think my own thoughts and there i
am driving along
but it turns out that that's not quite
right so
if most of the reason that we're having
such a strong sense of
automatic driving is that most of the
time when you're driving nothing is
happening
and you're just going along and the
world's just flowing by
there's no there's no action to be taken
but as soon as you have to take action
it tends to scramble any other
activity you're engaged in so an
everyday example of that is that
almost invariably if you suddenly have
to break
suddenly while driving you'll certainly
stop speaking um
nowhere no one carries out a fluid
conversation and keeps on going while
slamming on the emergency stop
um everybody stops and you have to um
and the experimental work by
harold pachler at his lab at ucsd have
shown this
in a simulated driving task where they
give people a task of following along a
car in a very simple
driving world and the car occasionally
breaks and you've got to slam the breaks
of your car
um it's not a real car it's just it's
all just joystick stuff
um in a virtual environment but when you
do that
you you simultaneously you you're asked
questions very simple questions like i
think something something like
for example one version is you you get a
tone and you have to just say
was the tone high or low and you have to
say it's too soon no
no physical use of a keyboard or
anything
um but it turns out that if if if you
ask me whether a tone a beep is high or
low
while i'm breaking i can't do both i
just have to do the breaking get a
breaking out of the way and then i think
all right
what was that question and then i
answered the question so
even something where um the task in the
world is very simple
and the task the two things you've got
to do say was that tone high or low or
just keep the car on the road and break
when you need to they seem like totally
independent things but actually they get
tangled up
so i think it makes all these sort of
remarkable cases like the fact that
people can
type and play the piano and and chat at
the same time do those
those things it makes even more amazing
because it really is the exception
rather than the rule
cool let's move on to our next topic
those who people who listen to the show
regularly know that it's one of my
obsessions which is
attention in fact i've been known to say
that
we are our attention and it has you know
implications in all kinds of things like
for instance
you know social media is constantly
working to hijack our attention
you know etc and the idea of attention's
been moved over into ai
for instance some of the newest work in
linguistic
processors like the gpt-3 thing that a
lot of us have heard about recently
which is this amazing
piece of software from open ai that
seems to have learned a scary amount of
language by
processing a trillion words or something
you give it a
root and it goes off to the races and
creates text it uses
a technology called transformer networks
which actually uses attention
as part of its model so one of the
things that
is non-intuitive about our brain
states and i think has huge implications
for the contents of our memory
is this idea of the unity of attention
that it's single threaded
mostly with some exceptions that you
talk about and that
it processes by single steps in fact in
my own work where i
attempt to build simulated consciousness
how about that but for a white-tailed
deer
not a human i actually make that
attention thing discreet
basically just have it change every 250
milliseconds or not
either changes or it doesn't based on a
whole bunch of conditions etc
but it's just single steps through
basically one object at a time which
then activates a different brain state
etc
so you go in quite a bit about this this
idea of the unity of attention and how
it emerges from the concept of the whole
brain or near whole brain
processing so tell us about attention
and how this fits in with your model
so yes i think jim you the way you
framed the
question actually encapsulates the way i
i think i think one should see this
which is to think of ourselves to think
say that i am my
my um my attention my focus of attention
and i am essentially a sequence of
attentional snippets
um i think that's a very very useful way
to think
um so it's very easy for us to imagine
that as well as the things i was tending
to
my brain's engaged in all kinds of other
activities and it's certainly doing some
things it's certainly driving my
heart i don't want to worry about last
night it's making me breathe
sort of practical housekeeping things um
but i would
want to argue that really um
most of the most of the activity of your
brain is focusing on whatever you're
actively doing now so if you're speaking
if you're
playing a maybe playing a golf stroke
if you're focusing on some music that's
pretty much
your brain's primary primary business
it's it's pretty much entirely focused
on
on that one thing and there'll be some
peripheral activity going on here and
there but
it's not for example the case that while
i
think um i'm
chatting to a friend as a chunk of my
brain which is wondering about a tricky
problem i was stuck on yesterday
or there's another part of my brain
which is sort of worrying about my
finances or
there's another part of the brain which
is processing some resentment about some
past life from a work colleague or all
of this is i think
completely completely wrong and your
brain is a because it's such a
serial processor it's only really one
complex thing it's time
if he's doing one thing it's not doing
anything else um so it
it's really right thing for your brain
essentially
taking on one challenge at a time step
by step
every few hundred milliseconds is grab
making a new
stab thinking let me look from here to
there or move from word to word i'll
review a thought i'll think i can follow
on with another thought
i'll look at another part of the an
image
um but it's a pretty slow process which
pretty much blocks out everything else
we do have an intuitive sense of being
very serial i think as a struggling to
do more than one thing at once
and yet as with the grand illusion we
also have a sense that oh yeah but
while i'm doing this thing i can i can
see a fully detailed world and i can
hear all the sounds around me and i can
feel my body on the chair well i can now
i think about it but but
i couldn't before and i think we also do
have a sort of
implicit sort of intuition that and i'm
doing lots of covert pondering as well
particularly if you're
taking a sort of death psychology
perspective you have the idea that
there's all kinds of
pondering of unexpected issues in
unexpected ways which
is going on in the background but i
think there's no real evidence that
that's the case but i think the brain is
really because it's because of its the
way it's built the fact is this this big
distributed system it's really hard for
that system to work on what two problems
at once with the same machinery
yeah i've actually found that to be and
very interesting and challenging
assertion on your part and as i thought
about i said you're probably right
i will confess to being a person who has
long believed in the background
processing because i
sort of felt it in myself right i've
often written software as part of the
work that i do
and you know not being a professional
software developer
you know i can easily paint myself into
corners and things right
and at you know four o'clock in the
afternoon i go [ __ ] it man i just can't
make any progress here
let me go sleep on it and i'm sure i'll
have the answer in the morning and
amazingly often
i do but you gave a very interesting
alternative
way of looking at that and i suspect
that you're right maybe you could talk a
little bit about
your idea of resetting and get rid of
assumptions etc
and an alternative argument for the
phenomena that we can
mistake as background processing
yeah i think this is a very powerful
intuition that we all share that
you you try to solve something you can't
you come back and then suddenly it's
clear
and it is very easy to imagine that
what's been going on and this is
an old idea going back to in fact as a
strand of gestalt psychology
you mentioned earlier on that there's
this idea of incubation
incubation problem solving the problems
being mulled over
um intrusively even though you're not
actively addressing it
and i think the uh the alternative and
it's not something that's an
old idea in cognitive psychology but i
think a very convincing one actually
uh is that there's something else is
going on so what's happening when you're
trying to solve a tricky problem is
you're searching
in space of solutions and you've got
you're in a cul-de-sac if you weren't in
a cul-de-sac you keep going and you
you just think i'm nearly there i
finally got it and you would keep going
till you've got it but in fact you
you stop and get baffled because you're
in a conversation
you can't don't know how to go forwards
so if you
um keep going you've somehow got to get
yourself out of the cultivation that's
often quite hard
in fact you've often thought about
possible ways out which clearly haven't
worked
because you you're still stuck it's very
hard to generate some
new perspective on the problem which
will get you out and what a break will
often do
is just reset so you just come at the
problem you've forgotten where you were
that's good
because where you were was bad you're in
a bad place you just start again
um and one so and so that's that's that
sense of
now it's obvious to me is because now
you've you've started from a different
place
and that place just happens to be better
often it won't be and something often
you'll just be in another bad place or
another
place which you have to explore for a
long time to work out whether it's
better or not
yeah the way i articulated to myself
when i read your theory
was that my brain activations are still
resonating away from the places i've had
attention say for the last half hour
right it's something greater or lesser
degree or somehow it's somehow impacting
the whole brain network everything i've
paid attention to
for a while right so it's you know the
brain state is conditioned by what i've
been thinking about for the half hour
and because i'm at a cul-de-sac as you
said those were not the right paths
right
and just stripping all that prior
history of attention out or at least
having it way lower activated the next
morning
allows me to whatever my internal
processes are we'll get to that in a
second
converge to something that's right and
it's in a different set of attractors
essentially and i will say it seems like
you quote some evidence that it's
essentially just random but
it doesn't feel like that to me i mean
again maybe this is another illusion
that i am way better the next morning on
solving a stuck point in programming
than i was at 4 30
in the afternoon the night before so it
doesn't feel random to me and it may be
that there's something deeper going
on and clearing out a large amount of
residual
brain resonances from kind of the steps
of attention
yeah and it's maybe that sleep is
somehow very important because i think
there's
some evidence that the rest and sleep
actually do
lead to a better better rebound effects
you get so so
from the perspective we've been
exploring you're more fundamentally
shifting your play your your attractor
and getting unstuck more effectively
so that does doesn't appear to be the
case but if you certainly if you're
trying to get experimental
evidence that people are really doing
incubation properly that is really
impossible this has proved to be
excruciatingly difficult to get any such
evidence
so the kind of thing you do is you give
people people given
done so many experiments where they give
people for example anagrams to solve
and something you can solve something
you can't once you can't just kind of go
round and round
no i just can't do it and so you then
give people a break and then they come
back and do them again and
you know it's very rarely the case that
they do much better
um after a break they maybe do a little
bit but it's really
um and the length of the break doesn't
seem to make much difference
so it's not as if you give them two
hours then they're much better they've
got all the anagram sources there
because they've had all that time to do
the processing
um no it's not really the case um you
know they may be marshalled better
because they're slightly less stuck
give them a nice sleep probably slightly
better but it's really much more
consistent with
uh sort of diffuse nudging you out of
your conversation rather than
my brain is just knocking off the
underground one after another solving
the world when i look back
yep and i should make a note for the
listener here that
just in this example nick gave us each
one of his
claims he has backed up with actual
evidence and it's well footnoted and the
footnotes actually have interesting
discussions so these aren't just dry
footnotes footnotes are worth reading
which is not always the case
for those who you know want to have some
sense of confidence and nick just isn't
making this [ __ ] up even though of
course he is based on his own theory
right absolutely
to myself yes i'm going to hop to
another topic it's one that
i wasn't convinced of but i'm not going
to say that
i'm right to not be convinced but i'm
sort of on the bubble
which is you argue that human
thinking basically has no principles in
it right
we're not really doing our thinking
based on principles we've somehow
extracted from
our thinking about the world and you
even make the you know to my mind fairly
extreme claim that even chess masters
have no principles
they basically are just sort of clever
at how they remember
real boards and i wasn't convinced by
that argument
and in fact let me play back the thing
that kind of caused my ears to go up
which is that you mentioned the
well-known result
the chess masters are no better than
anybody else at
recalling random boards but they are
way better at recalling the boards for
real games
that either they played or even any real
game you know just
show a chess master 10 positions from 10
random real games
and they'll remember them but they won't
remember random boards any better than
you or i
and i said wait a minute here doesn't
that say there's got to be some
principle that's been a filter
applied to perception that allows
the chess master to know implicitly at
least
that one was a real board and one was
another and
why that particularly resonated with me
my motivation for getting deeply into
cognitive science was something
surprisingly simple
through all my life i've played war
games back to the days when i was 10
years old
and they were little cardboard pieces
with tanks on them that you moved around
on a hexagonal paper board
through all the evolution of the online
stuff etc
and in 2012 i learned a new computerized
game called advanced
tactics gold which is very complicated
very realistic
very good and very hard at least so it
seemed
and i sat down learned to play it it
kicked my ass
bad the first couple of games i got a
little better a little better
and this is game way way way more
complex than go in fact
some calculations i did said the average
number of move possibilities
is 10 to the 60th per turn 10 to the
60th
as opposed to maybe 200 and go and
30 in chess and five or six in checkers
droughts
so anyway and then i also stopped and
thought about it a little bit how many
of these war games have i played in my
life
and gross estimate at that point was i
probably played
a game to conclusion 2500 times in my
life
which is a very low number compared to
machine learning
right continue to story advanced tactics
gold good game people if you like games
check it out it's on steam
after seven games i had basically
extracted enough and i would argue
applied my principles
enough so the sucker never beat me again
i probably played it a few hundred times
since then 100 times at least one every
time
sometimes difficult to win but i've won
and you know what we know about
machine learning there's no way you
could get that good on only playing
a hundred times impossible right there
has to be something else going on
so that's my push back on no principles
yeah
well i think it depends what you count
as a principle because i think what
you're
pushing back on is something i'm
extremely sympathetic to so
if you think about how machine learning
works
as a model for the mind which i think is
an interesting thing to do
then the shocking thing is that it needs
so much data
exactly as you're saying you've got this
enormous space of possible games
and you play in a tiny subspace and you
and you've
learned to play pretty well and and and
start to
start to win even though you can't
possibly be doing that
by in some simple-minded way comparing
the current um game with previous games
because the space is just way way too
big
um now i think that's absolutely true so
one
one view of what's going on is that the
brain must have
the ability that machine learning
systems don't have to work out some
underlying as it was sort of perhaps
quasi-mathematical
set of rules of rules which tell you how
to play well
so instead of just thinking oh i've seen
a position like this before
and i did this and it didn't work i'll
do something else or
it did work so i'll do it again instead
of doing something like that
you're somehow breaking breaking out and
having some sort of general
understanding such a general theory of
how to play the game
now i think that is wrong i think the
brain doesn't do that very well
and we have intuitions about how we play
chess or go or any game um but the
intuitions are pretty poor so when
as i'm sure you know when people started
to build chess playing computers they
one of the first things they had to go
at is just asking chess players
um well what how did you create you've
got to play good chess
which is a very sensible thing to do and
but actually chest pose can't say very
much they can certainly say things like
well the queen you don't want to lose
your queen and
don't rush your king into an attack
that's actually a mistake and control
the center of the board
and and other things which are not not
worthless
but they are fairly even complete and
minimal so famously
um you have books uh also some great
russian grand master has a wonderful
wonderfully titled book which is
something like principles of chess
strategy or something
and what does the book contain what it
contains is a stack of cool examples
like famous games puzzle tricky problems
with an explanation intuitive
explanation of how to deal with this
kind of case
now but what it doesn't do is say now
the principles of chess here they are
and of course the if we if we knew the
principles of chess if they
were um that would be useful then
obviously
building chest pain computers would be
much easier than tears
so i think the right lesson to draw from
that kind of case is to think well
what's interesting about human learning
this is what the
prince of quote supposed principles of
chess book is telling you is
it's saying think deeply and
reflectively and thoughtfully about the
cases you encounter
so you're not just storing them as it
were as raw data thinking if i see raw
data it looks a bit like this again i
know what to do
you're not doing that you're thinking in
a very rich
metaphorical and logical way of thinking
now what's going on here
what kind of thing is this have i seen
anything a bit
like this before and i think this is the
ability that's really
astonishing that makes us so remarkable
it's not that
we can play chess by working out sort of
as a worse of mathematical principles
about what to do how to play every chess
game
but what we can do is think this
position i'm in now reminds me
possibly implicitly of a number of other
positions in those positions
there's the kind of thing i did was this
so probably this is the kind of thing
i'm going to do now so it's a
higher more abstract level now how that
works how the brain is able to
operate at this more abstract level so
that it can
learn not just from the very specific
ball position but they're classical
positions i mean how that
that works is the kind of holy grail of
cognitive science and ai in my view it's
kind of thing that doug have hofstrata
that was it was doing so much so much
work on
40 years ago and and for ongoing to try
to understand sort of fluidity and
creativity of our
ability to deal with particular
experiences extracting sort of
analogically
this this is the case a bit like that
previous case um and doing that in a way
that is
is sort of coherent and that's that's
remarkable we can do it but i think
that's what we're doing
um because if we were producing
principles well first of all we never
people can never articulate them but
also most complicated
problems and your game will absolutely
one of these i'm sure there's no real
algorithm the algorithm if there is an
algorithm to play to play that game well
it's almost certainly
a very memory based algorithm it's in
situations like this do this in
situations like this do this other thing
it won't be a something sort of more
abstract than that
so i think if you want to call those
principles that more abstract way of
seeing the world
then that's that that's that's that i
think that absolutely is what the brain
is doing
but what it's not doing i think is is
producing a
set of rules are a kind of abstract
theory which is a consistent
understanding of
how to play the game or how the world
works or anything of that kind
yeah i agree 100 in fact the word i
always use i didn't use principles i
just used your word principles
i call those heuristics and in fact my
mission
and i don't know if i'll succeed because
i'm too old god damn it i wish i'd
started this when i was younger instead
of when i was
60 years old is heuristic induction
how is it that we induce heuristics
because there's no doubt about
at least based on my introspection but
as you point out our introspection is
dubious when i'm playing my game or any
games and
in fact since i did all that work with
advanced tactics gold i even got the
source code from the developer and
wrote some evolutionary algorithms that
improved his ai
i've played some other games and i just
see again and again and again
i develop heuristics which are
definitely not algorithms you can't say
that these
five or six or seven rules of thumb
for that particular game are quite
enough to win
but if you have a brain that's been
tuned to extract
patterns from games you can then apply
the heuristics in a pretty
straightforward fashion
for instance is a whole class of games
where it's really important
that you keep your line consistent
across the board so guys can't get past
you
right kind of true in chess but really
true in some of these military games
and then there's also one of the things
you learn when you play one of these
games
is the relative efficacy of defense
versus attack
for instance having played several
hundred titles over my life maybe a
thousand now probably several hundred
a meta pattern is that often
it turns out to be true in real life in
war as well
that it's often better to take the
tactical defensive and get the other guy
to attack you first and then
counter-attack
right that turned out to have been the
tactical brilliance of the german army
in world war
ii particularly in the later phases of
the war
so this is heuristics and how we induce
heuristics from these otherwise flat
patterns i think
is still a huge open question and is
right at the very core of my own
interest in this space
yeah and i think i think as you were
hinting it's at the very core of
intelligence really
and what is astonishing is that is that
we can
produce these sort of rough patterns
heuristics and so on
and they um they are as you say they're
not sufficient on their own to solve the
problem if you coded those
into a computer that would it wouldn't
be a winning computer it wouldn't be a
winning system on its own
um but if you put that together with a
creative flexible brain that can somehow
know which heuristic is the right one to
deploy and when there's a clash thing no
no this is clearly a case but this one
much more important than that one but
there may be some other case where the
when it
where it's the reverse that ability to
kind of knit together
a difference of these heuristics is very
um it's very remarkable
um and i think you know it's we are we
do forget just how
unbelievably good we are at
finding complicated patterns in very
small amounts of data
and so in fact you can play a game the
normal space of possible moves and get
pretty good at it quickly that's very
interesting
um similarly and science manages to
produce principles and it really does
produce principles they're not in the
heads of the scientists directly with
other things we actually
produce as a community the same in
sciences which would be very
successful such as physics um you know
amazingly it turns out you can produce
um a relatively small number of
principles which explain a huge amount
of
of reality and so you know but you're
not doing that by
as it was surveying the universe and
just taking in as much data as you
possibly can in fact
you're narrowing down a tiny tiny amount
of data you know
carefully dropping balls down slopes of
different inclines and
carefully watching pendulums go
backwards and forwards and remarkably it
turns out that
you're doing this leads you to
generalizations which which helps you
understand
the universe as a whole it's just an
amazing thing and
but it really doesn't work by being a
kind of data hoover uh the way the way
that machine learning is
which is the kind of take your trigger
words retrieving images and just find
some
find the structure in all of them the
human brain seems to work in a really
different way
yeah it is interesting and you know and
we alluded to it a little bit in passing
that one of the other cutting edge
things you know learning on small data
is something people are quite aware of
as the distinction between humans and
data in fact i noticed you had in your
acknowledgement section my friend
josh tenenbaum has done a lot of work
on small sample learning and ways that
are rather different than brute force
machine learning and you know this is
very hot area but anyway
the other area where this is there's a
lot of tension right now is about
language
right particularly with the new 3 out
which we alluded to earlier is this
massive
trillion word database that's been
processed by
several billion node deep learning
network to produce a language model
and it's scary how good it is however it
does not appear
to actually understand language it
doesn't take a genius to figure out how
to trick it
and so probably human language learning
is something different than just
brute force pattern matching on a
trillion words well you know frankly we
know we don't get exposed to a trillion
words
we have pretty good mastery of language
by the time we're what you guys work on
that language three or four years old
right
yeah that's great for you pretty good
yeah yeah again something like
principles something like
probably not chomsky and universal
grammar but something like that
maybe it's there well i think i think
again
it's going back to the point that
cognition for me is perception
i i want to see all of these cases as
cases where
you're abstracting from specific
concrete experiences but you may be
abstracting at quite a high level of
generality
so in learning a language you see
something like what christians
and i have been thinking about a lot of
the last few years you should think of
learning a language as learning a skill
which might intuitively sound to most
people as
very natural of course it's learning a
skill is
no more or less than playing a piano or
learning to play a sport
um or need a game um but traditionally
it's not viewed like that it's viewed as
uh at least in chomsky's perspective
it's viewed as
a problem of learning a body of
knowledge but not a body of knowledge
which
tells you how what sentences are
allowed in your language and how they're
composed and that abstract body of
knowledge
is a real target of learning and that is
supposed to take you
far beyond mere skill learning um but i
think
the approach that maureen and i and
others many others
would take is to see language as
an abstraction from lots and lots of
concrete experiences so what you're
learning
is you're learning specific words you're
learning specific patterns of words
you're learning specific relationships
between
singulars and plurals and so on in verbs
and nouns and all of these patterns
and constructions are there is the term
of art in linguistics at the moment
that's the
um the movement construction grammar
specifications takes the
that takes this kind of perspective
you're seeing the
task of learning languages learning all
these little micro patterns
and they gradually build up and interact
to give you a complicated system
which is the system system of language
we that we speak
but really you're learning it sort of
piece by piece by piece but you're
learning it as a
as a set of sort of chunks of
information so chunks of knowledge
you're learning
about particular um particular noun verb
nouns and which verbs they go with
you're learning particularly about how
certain kind of endings work
um and you're not as it were just
blitzing
lip releasing the the entire corpus that
you've ever heard
and you'll find finding these patterns
of building up those patterns they're
building
incrementally more and more so i suppose
there's some very interesting
so step-by-step process of learning
that we're engaging in when we're
learning a language which is very
different from the kind of blitz
that the machine learning system will do
which allows us
to learn from very small samples but the
typical child will hear a few million
up to perhaps 30 million or so
in a very high linguistic input
household so 30 million words a year
so you a four year old might have heard
it might between 10 and 100 million
depending on the household
words most of which it would have been
paying no attention to and
probably made no difference at all but
it's
way too little as you say than for a
machine learning system
and the child's also got the problem of
course of doing all the phonology just
looking at what were those sounds um
how do i i don't know just understanding
the speech signal as an acoustic object
and translating that acoustic
stimulus into a symbolic form that
itself is a huge learning task
so the child's learning fee is pretty
pretty remarkable
indeed indeed we're you know running a
little bit short on time here i'm going
to skip over a whole section on folk
physics folk biology and folk psychology
and the failure of good old-fashioned ai
which is more or less implied by the
failure of those two but i would
encourage listeners to read the book and
go into that
something that i think is going to be of
real interest to folks
is i thought a very clever
set of arguments on the nature of
emotion
we think of oh you know i'm feeling you
know anger or whatever that it's a pure
emotion well
you know there's this distinction
between emotions and feelings
in the cognitive science literature
emotions in the body feelings in the
head roughly speaking
and you give some very clever examples
on how that's probably right
and one i had forgotten all about the
kuleshov effect
so maybe if you talk a little bit about
how your overall model
predicts actually i think accurately
sort of body plus context equals emotion
something like that
yes absolutely so so perhaps i'll start
with the kudos effect so lev
kuderschoff was a a soviet director in
the early part of the 20th century
and he noticed the effect the the
the effect that bears his name which is
if you show
us say even still other could also be
moving a still image of
a person and you change the context
they're in although this image of them
is exactly exactly the same then they
will um the viewer will interpret the
facial expression differently
so the famous example is is of a one of
his actors even mozuki
who has a rather impassive expression in
the example
that is in the book and you place him
next to a picture
of a dead child as you mock up with each
other but it's a
sad looking picture of a child in a
coffin
and you look at his face and you look at
the coffin you think he's expressing
misery
this desperate sense of sadness which is
controlling it
but you can see it's there very
powerfully um and yet
if you place the same um the same face
beside a um a picture of
a bowl of soup which doesn't look
particularly appetizing soup
but mysteriously um he starts to look
hungry and he looks like he wants to eat
the soup
and if you put and then the final one is
he's got an attractive woman lying and
she's long and you think ah he's going
to see his lust to his eyes you know
he's hiding it well it's quite subtle so
this
sense that we're able to project and do
project um a different
emotion into a into a face is i think
very interesting
now the thing is that i think that's a
very good
indication of what's going on when we're
interpreting our own body state
so instead of looking at even music in
face i'm also
of course in my daily life i'm trying to
interpret my own physiology
so i've got very simple model of my own
physiology for
i know roughly how much adrenaline's
floating around um i know whether i'm
feeling
positively attracted to a stimulus or
wanting to recoil from it
but there's not actually a lot more than
that um it's not that's not it but
that's
like you know this is adrenaline for
example correlate with my breathing
heart rate and so on
they're very really a very simple
underlying
physiological system that i'm aware of
um so that
means that if i have a particular
physiological reaction i have to think
to myself well
what's going on here now what's why is
this reaction coming from rather like do
i like looking at even even as a kid's
rather impassive face
and work it out as with um with the face
i look at the context
so i find myself in a situation where
well let me take let me give a famous
example of a bridge crossing experiment
which is a lovely experiment yeah i love
that one
that was like a hammer hitting me in the
head when i read that
yeah yeah so this is a this is a
wonderful experiment done in the
university of british columbia in about
1974 i think
by a couple of a pair of brilliant
social psychologists so they
they station attractive women who are
experimenters
who are holding a clipboard at one end
of two bridges
and one bridge is a wobbly bridge um
which is a
suspension bridge which is actually
quite a scary bridge to walk across
sort of moves around as you walk i think
um and another bridge is just some
regular bridge down down as a word
ground level this is an
area where lots of uh undergraduates
walk through that picking off
um male undergraduates and giving them
their
questions and they say at the end oh by
the way for
ethical reasons i have to give you a
chance to follow up through any
questions
so here's my phone number and there
really aren't any questions that would
have arisen um
in this uh change but the phone number's
there
and of course the bridge crosser might
think oh well i was a very attractive
woman um
shall i give her a call just you know
just to to get to know her better
and so and indeed sure enough uh well
there are two things that are
interesting
that they measured one is how many of
the bridge crosses ask for the number
and how many don't and then how many of
those that did ask remember how many did
they actually actually call
now it turns out that you get something
like 50 or so percent more
of asking for the number and calling for
people who've walked across the high
bridge
now what's going on there you might
think this how can that be relevant
but it is relevant of course from the
perspective of trying to understand your
own feelings
uh through your monitoring of physiology
because what happens to those people on
the high bridge they walk across the
high bridge it's quite scary
so that leads to all kinds of adrenaline
flooding around the system
then they meet the experimenter and they
think
well i just need to have this incredible
adrenaline rush
wow i mean the only reason it must be
because this person is just somehow
connecting with me in some fundamental
way um i'll
i'll get her number and call um of
course in practice
the adrenaline rush is is the bridge but
we're not seeing it that way because
we're locked into the conversation we're
having now and
that's that's you know that's our
interpretation of our
um experience is a tremendous feeling of
interest and attraction
in this person and that that phenomenon
i think is is very very general so
another example much more prosaic
example but rather clever
there's some experiments by danny
oppenheimer um psychologist now carnegie
mellon
he's done many many clever experiments
in this kind of thing but one very
simple one
is that you give people pictures of
luxury cars
which are either bad you're well
photocopied um so
so the first thing is if you ask people
which car they prefer
they tend to prefer the well photocopied
car and you're not asking about the
picture they're asking about the car
but if they see a crumbly photographed
luxury card
well i don't know i just don't do like
that so much now ef on the other hand so
the same thing so i'm looking at the
the image and i'm thinking i'm just
generally feeling a slightly icky queasy
just unsettled feeling about that image
what's wrong with that
what's wrong with the image of course
the answer is well it's badly
photocopied that's wrong with it what's
wrong with it but we don't
interpret it that way we just think well
i'm looking at a car and
i'm feeling visually a bit unhappy
probably it's because
it's a car i don't really like the
wonderful thing about danny's experiment
is he has an extra condition where
he tells he tells people i'm so sorry
we had real problems with the
photocopier so some of these images are
terrible
and then the effects doesn't completely
go away i think but it largely goes away
do you do as soon as people know oh
right yeah
it's a beautiful car but a crummy
photograph close to coffee then they're
okay
so similarly i think in the bridge
crafting experiment had the
experimenter reminded people oh you've
just walked across the bridge how much
adrenaline do you feel maybe that if
that would have been the question
what's the what's the been the effect of
walking across that bridge bridge on
on how you feel then they'd have thought
oh yeah right of course the adrenaline's
coming from the bridge not from
the experimenter and so that's that's a
clue that it's
it's interpretative the sense of emotion
a sense of attraction to a person
attraction to a car
sense of fear of walking across a bridge
and whatever it may be these are
interpretative states you're
trying to work out what your body is
telling you in just the same way that
looking at an ambiguous face
you'll try to work out what that face is
is meaning
and you to do that you're taking account
of the context
as well as your body but you're not it's
not the case that the emotion is in any
sense
welling up from within fully interpreted
it doesn't it doesn't come from within
you
with its uh wearing it's a concert on
its face as it were
rather than you've got physiological
response contextual situation
and the interpretative brain is churning
away and thinking
i know what this is it must be this um
but often of course
those interpretations are wrong that's
really a powerful insight i must say
and you give a very interesting example
of the potential dangers of thinking the
opposite you tell the story of bertrand
russell
and you know his internalized view that
he no longer
loved his wife talk about that a little
bit and some of the dangers
of assuming that these emotional states
are
deeper than they actually are i think
this is
something we all have to be really
careful of yeah so bertrand russell is
cycling i think near grand chester
and he has a some thunderbolt sense that
he doesn't love his wife
and although in fact no marriage then
continues on for many years
i think um it's at that point sort of
all over and it's just a matter of
um escape uh and and
gradual extrication um and i think that
his mental model and fox virgin russia
was a phenomenal genius
so not not through lack of sophisticated
sophisticated thinking
this mental model of what's going on in
emotions is
from time to time your true feelings
just burst forth and when they burst
forth you've just got to know that
that's that's my real feeling there it
is
you know i just got to act on that um
but she did um now that maybe it may
or may not have been the right thing to
do but i think not for that reason
because i think this sense that we have
of
of deep things welling up deep thoughts
welling up from within is just
fundamentally fundamentally extremely
forced and illusory and a similar
thought is that um
in in heating discussions with our loved
ones we can quite often find people
saying things
that one has that feeling of well that's
what you really think there now that's
the truth has come out at last
and i think again that's a very
dangerous perspective to have we should
view ourselves much more as
creative fiction spinners who can
produce a fiction
of one type and of the reverse type and
not and neither the listener nor the
person creating the fiction is really
should be really sure quite what story
is the right one
so that sort of sense that there's a
kind of rubicon you can actually
accidentally pass
or that some sort of true insight which
will come to you and
there's no way back i think it's a very
dangerous one we should be very wary of
that
yeah i think that's really good advice
the theme throughout the book is that
what's really in our brain is both
sparse and inconsistent so
don't take it as seriously as we
sometimes do right
because it's provisional the brain's
just making this [ __ ] up on the fly the
confabulator i've used that term for a
long time since i became aware of
gazanika's work
i wish we could go into gazanica but
we're short on time let's move on to
some applied stuff
now with all this idea that it's
provisional it's confabulation it's
sparse it's
inconsistent nonetheless we have built
up
culture right and culture takes
all this isn't consistency and
sparseness and sort of gets co-created
with some attempts to put stakes in the
ground
and you know i was thinking of some
extreme examples one of which
is the catholic catechism as a kid i was
raised a catholic until i rebelled
against it at age 11. i've told the
story on the podcast a few times
but it was pretty powerful system of
indoctrination right so you just repeat
it again and again and again you write
down memory traces and
you can spit out the answers to the 300
questions in the baltimore catechism by
the time you're nine years old
and then you look at you know marxist
leninism and their worship of the works
of marx and angles you know a good
marxist leninist could cough up marx
or angles justification for almost
anything
and then of course the similar systems
in other religions
whether it's hindu buddhism taoist and
cultures more generally
select certain representations for
maximum repetition
and that's what culture seems to be yeah
i think that's absolutely right no i
think that's something deeply true about
that
um and i think to extend we should think
of ourselves
as as as traditions so each each
each of us is a is a tradition of which
basically consisting of all our past
thoughts of actions so there's this
incredible degree to which um we have we
because of our flow of experience and
our continual flow of attention hopping
from one
one thing to another we built up this
enormous repertoire of experience and
that will condition the way we
think about new things so we just want
to stress
that that we are incredibly rich
sophisticated beings and we reach
through our
ability to tap into our own history and
our own tradition but of course we're
not just our own tradition
actually many of the things we know come
from other people in fact we're
collecting
we collectively create cultural
traditions which are far more
elaborate than any individual could
create but that does also
mean that it's possible to try to coerce
or corral people in a particular
direction
by by putting various sort of cultural
stakes in the ground and saying
whenever um whatever you think about any
anything
this is one thing we all take to be
jubitable
and to have as a list of sort of basic
basic truths
and even though those truths may be very
hard to understand so
you may have people who are uh convinced
of some religious truth
so for example the trinity beings are
three in one which is very hard to know
what that
really what it is exactly one's
believing but one can think well
i've been taught this is right it's very
important and i believe it well possibly
i've been taught it's not right
and it's very important so i definitely
don't believe it but whatever it is
whichever way around it is
one can have an extremely strong sense
of this is an important conviction to
hold on to and defend
even without a really clear sense of
what it is that one is holding on to and
defending
and so i think we should we should
always be skeptical of stakes in the
ground if all states should be movable
yeah i think that's one of the things
that comes out of that work very
strongly and i hope disseminates out
into the world
is that all this stuff is provisional
it's inconsistent it's sketchy
and so don't believe that [ __ ] right
unless you can find objective evidence
that reinforces it you know and it
points to me
even more the importance of the
scientific
frame of mind and i'm sure i'm going to
piss off some of my post-modernist
friends here
you know the liberal universalist mind
right that
doesn't try to go from theory to
everything and believes in tolerance
and empiricism essentially as ways to
engage with the world that we should be
suspicious of these stakes in the ground
this has been a wonderful conversation i
didn't get to all my notes by any sets
of the
imagination yep so well thanks so much
jim i mean it's been a huge pleasure to
be on the show
and lots of great questions and lots
also for me to think about more and i
very much hope some of your listeners
have found this this useful and
interesting and um and
i hope it helps all of us just think a
little bit more about
how both how we do work how little we
know how we work
and also the fact that we shouldn't be
too sure about
both any of our beliefs but certainly
not any of our beliefs about our minds
indeed well this has been wonderful i've
enjoyed the hell out of it and i'm glad
i had the opportunity to read the book a
second time
and to come closer at least to your
point of view
production services and audio editing by
jared james consulting
music by tom muller at modern space
music